Register of the UFA motion picture newsreels
Hoover Institution Archives
UFA motion picture newsreels
1933-1945
48007
Hoover Institution Archives
450 motion picture film reels, 3 envelopes (45.1 linear feet)
The UFA motion picture newsreels depict German military operations and conditions in Germany during World War II, mainly during the 1939-1942 period. Includes a few pre-war newsreels of Nazi leaders and rallies, and a few photographs. Most newsreels were distributed in Spain.
UFA (Firm)
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1948.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the library catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Collection(s)
Ernest D. Rose papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Historical Note
Universum Film AG (UFA) is a German film production company that was founded in 1917. At its inception, UFA was envisioned as a state-controlled vehicle for military propaganda films, but the company greatly expanded its output in 1918 to include feature films, documentaries, newsreels, and public service films. With a broadened focus that was further spurred on by the 1921 privatization of the company, UFA made an especially significant impact on world cinema during the Weimar Republic era (1919-1933), most notably through its German Expressionist films.
In 1937, all German film companies were nationalized under the Third Reich (1933-1945). UFA and its competitors were brought under the oversight of the Third Reich’s propaganda ministry, and Joseph Goebbels, in his role as propaganda minister, oversaw production. Initially, UFA maintained some autonomy and continued success with production and distribution of feature films, but under Goebbel’s increasing control, the propagandistic appeal of newsreels ultimately dominated the company’s focus. Wartime news films favoring a National Socialist point of view were widely distributed to both German and international audiences.
In 1940, prompted by the Nazi invasion of Poland and efforts to sway public opinion in support of the German war effort, the Third Reich combined newsreel companies Ufa-Tonwoche and Deulig-Tonwoche (both under the broader UFA umbrella), as well as Tobis-Woche and Fox-Tönende-Wochenshau, into a single weekly war newsreel titled Die Deutsche Wochenshau (DW). With reports that doors were often closed and even locked in many German theaters during DW screenings, German audiences were literally held captive by the footage.
As the single DW newsreel emerged, the foreign weekly newsreel, or Auslandtonwoche (ATW), was restructured and refocused, again in support of the German war effort and particularly in support of the Polish campaign. ATW was distributed to occupied and neutral countries alike. Initially, ATW and DW newsreels differed only by language. As ATW operations grew, the newsreels were customized to their respective target audiences. Although ATW and DW reels contained similar content, scenes were often edited and German nationalism toned down in ATW reels to appeal to wider regional interests. Regional ATW editorial offices were also set up in select countries, including Belgium and Spain.
Shortly after merging all German newsreels into a single war newsreel, Goebbels combined all German film production companies into a single, state-run film monopoly called UFA-Film GmbH (UFI). UFA, Tobis, Terra, and other film companies were assimilated into UFI. This overarching state control of German film production resulted in censorship and selectively edited scenes in newsreels. In DW and ATW reels, scenes of dead German soldiers, as well as scenes of significant military failures on the Eastern Front, such as in the Battle of Stalingrad, were cut from final versions.
Though selectively edited to support the broader Nazi agenda, the combined efforts of DW and ATW generated a cinematic product unlike any other. With a drive to influence audiences from across Europe and beyond, these newsreels employed compelling and dramatic cinematic techniques, which set them apart from their American and European counterparts. American newsreels were modeled on newspapers that led with headline news stories, followed by news segments of decreasing importance. DW and ATW films, in contrast, were edited in a fashion similar to narrative movies, featuring seamless fades and dissolves between scenes and a build-up of story and action to a climactic turning point or conclusion. War scenes captured by cameramen at the front lines of battle were also central to the drama and action of Nazi-era newsreels. Sound was likewise used for cinematic effect. Voice-over narration conveyed a sense of continuity and authority, while dramatic music amplified the intensity of the visuals and narration.
These newsreels serve as significant historical documentation of World War II and a National Socialist perspective of the world. In addition to the UFA and Tobis newsreels at the Hoover Institution Archives, other known collections of these newsreels exist at the University of California at Los Angeles Film and Television Archive, the Library of Congress, the Imperial War Museum in London, and the Bundesarchiv in Berlin.
Scope and Content of Collection
The UFA motion picture newsreels, produced by the Third Reich, depict German military operations and conditions in Germany during World War II, mainly during the 1939-1942 period, in the form of the German weekly newsreel, or Die Deutsche Wochenshau (DW), and the foreign weekly newsreel, or Auslandtonwoche (ATW). Includes a few pre-war newsreels of Nazi leaders and rallies, and a few photographs. Most newsreels were distributed in Spain.
Propaganda, German--Spain.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns.; World War, 1939-1945--Germany.; Germany--History--1933-1945.; National socialism.; Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei.; Motion pictures.
- Motion Picture Films, 1939-1945 (Film shelf)
  Scope and Content note
  Motion picture newsreels produced by the Nazi government. The majority of the reels in the collection were produced by Universum Film AG (UFA), with a small amount coming from Tobis Wochenschau. Includes reels intended for domestic and international audiences. The bulk of this series covers the years 1940 to 1942. The overall content of the films varies greatly, including special political and military events, civilian life from all parts of Europe, and combat footage. Important figures present in the film include Adolf Hitler, Joseph Goebbels, Herman Göring, Heinrich Himmler, Benito Mussolini, and Francisco Franco.
  - Tobis, 1939-1945
    The films in this subseries were produced by Tobis and include 16mm and 35mm films. Gaps in sequence represent films that were never received by the archives.
    - Reels 1-4
    - Reels 6-16
    - Reels 18-19
    - Reels 21-29
    - Reel 31
  - UFA, Inland, 1939-1945
    The Inland versions of the reels were released domestically in Germany with German language soundtracks and include 16mm and 35mm films.
    Ausland versions also exist for the following reels: 519-521, 523-550, 555, 557-560, 562-572, 576-578, 581, and 586-587.
    The followings reels have not yet been described: 517, 518, 520, 521, 523, 555, 571-572, 576-578, 581-582, 586-587, 589, 596, 615, 621-622, 626, 628, and 633.
    Reel descriptions come from ledgers in the Ernest D. Rose papers.
    - Reel 519
      Scope and Contents note
      Comprised of 35mm reels.
      Part 1:
      1. Berlin, amateur German "sportsfest," first since war started; 2. Repatriation of Saarbrücken after armistice; 3. German kids enjoying vacation sponsored by Nationalsozialistische Volkswohlfahrt (NSV) (1 of 350 similar homes); 4. Heavy motorized cars and motorcycles, special mountain training; 5. Hitler Youth in naval training ship; 6. Steiermark, mining of iron ore and smelting; 7. Essen, Adolf Hitler visits home of Gustav Krupp on 70th birthday.
      Part 2:
      8. Berghof, General Dietrich gives report on fighting to Hitler; 9. Gauleiter of Steinmark talks with Hitler; 10. Paris, concert of German folk songs; 11. Waffen SS decorated with Iron Cross; 12. Front soldiers given Iron Cross, first shot of cameramen.
    - Reel 522
      Comprised of 35mm reels and 16mm reels.
      1. Ship yard, launching of ship; 2. Leipzig, International Trade Fair with 21 countries, Wehrmacht displaying captured Brit machines; 3. Coal mining; 4. POWs in forced labor; 5. Weimar, effects of British bombing; 6. Vienna, Segir Agreement, meeting with Hungary, Romania, Germany, Italy; 7. Budapest, German Cultural house; 8. Madrid, interned German civilians repatriated.
      9. Japan, German youth in Japan; 10. Copenhagen, track meet; 11. Italy, Il Duce (Mussolini) visits youth military school; 12. Orvieto, Duce visits women's gymnastic school; 13. Duce at new water wat for Tiber River; 14. Plymouth Harbor, Birmingham, Luftwaffe attack on British factory and harbor; 15. Kiel, Adm. Lutgen, U-Boat returns; 16. Ritter Cross given to PT boat captain; 17. PT boat prepares for sea.
    - Reel 524, 1940 September
      1. Metz, Himmler, and Dietrich review Waffen SS troops; 2. Warsaw, German Labor Service parading with Hierl and Kiel; 3. Belgium, German troops with captured British vehicles; 4. French Coast, German troops blow up British mines; 5. Mediterranean, Italian planes bomb British ships; 6. Map of Europe and British Isles; 7. Luftwaffe squadron preparing and then bombing British airfield.
    - Reel 525, 1940 September
      1. Norway, boys and girls voluntary harvesting in fields; 2. Hungary-Romania, Hungarian soldiers reoccupy border; 3. Berlin, Ley and Himmler greet Ramon Serrano Suner, review troops, and look at Volkswagens; 4. Germany, General Kerotzi meets with General Ritter von Epp; 5. Saarbrücken, Minister Todt, Gauleiter Balkerstadt(?) observe parade; 6. Factory workers; 7. Production of electric generators; 8. Manufacturing sea mines; 9. Sailors laying mines at sea; 10. Production of boots; 11. Injured soldiers in physical therapy.
      12. German soldiers cleaning tanks; 13. Artillery observers in balloon; 14. Sollum, Italian planes bombing British positions; 15. Bielefeld, British bombing on children's home; 16. N. France, Goering inspects Luftwaffe troops; 17. Bombers taking off for bombing run over England.
    - Reel 526, 1940 October
      Comprised of acetate 35mm and 16mm reels.
      1. Peking, British troops leave N. China for Hong Kong; 2. Bucharest, King of Romania welcomes back Queen Mother with parade; 3. Rome, von Ribbentrop, Count Ciano, talks in Italy with Duce; 4. Berlin, 27 Sept., Ciano, von Ribbentrop, Hitler, Kurusu, signing of Tripartite Pact; 5. Berlin, performances to raise money for BHJ; 6. Merchant marine cadets training; 7. Berlin, Goebbels, at UFA Palace opening of winter season for film festivals; 8. Workers canning food and baking.
    - Reel 527
      1. Washington, 27 Aug., Roosevelt signs bill to activate national guard; 2. US national guard inspected and get new uniforms; 3. Chungking, China, Japanese planes bombing Chungking; 4. Copenhagen, King Christian celebrates 70th birthday; 5. Bremmer Pass, 2 October 1940, Hitler and Mussolini meet for first time since war started; 6. Hanover, Italian minister Farinacci visiting Germany, with Goebbels, Dietrich, Victor Lutze; 7. Sweden, Spanish officers visit artillery school; 8. Berlin, exhibit on air industry; 9. Hitler Youth training with gliders; 10. Glider launched from water; 11. Luxemburg, volunteers officially join German forces; 12. Iron ore factories and mines.
      Parts 2:
      13. France, von Brauchitsch invites French Gauleiters to battlefield; 14. Oslo, ships delivering supplies; 15. Distribution of ration cards; 16. Libya, 17 September, Italian troops capture Sidi Barani; 17. British ships attack and sink French ships; 18. German mine sweepers in Channel; 19. Liverpool, German bombers on night attack of England.
    - Reel 528
      1. Rome, workers construct a bridge; 2. Rome, Minister of Education Rust given honorary doctorate; 3. Madrid, German military band playing concert; 4. Tangier, Spanish Marines go ashore and occupy former French city; 5. Bulgaria, Bulgarian troops reoccupy area; 6. Sophia, King Boris attends thank you parade; 7. Galati, Romania, German Resettlement Commission march through city.
      8. Oslo, Norwegian People's Voluntary Army march in parade; 9. Warsaw, retrospect of invasion and parade marking one year German occupation; 10. Troops going through tank training; 11. La Havre, French and German firefighters put out blaze started by RAF attack; 12. Artillery crew shells Dover; 13. Luftwaffe bombs England and dogfight RAF; 14. German naval fleet leaving port.
    - Reel 529
      1. Burma, Burma Road reopened; 2. Bulgaria, Bulgarian cavalry troops reenter territory given back; 3. Bucharest, Prince Michael parades through city; 4. Padua, Mussolini reviews parade of young fascists; 5. Harz, Ger., Reich youth leader Axsmann inspects Hitler Youth; 6. Berlin, Minister of Agriculture Walter Darre, Goebbels meet with Hitler.
      7. Wheat field being harvested; 8. München, art exhibition; 9. Berlin, large crowd in attendance of state funeral for Admiral von Trotha; 10. München, injured soldiers at rehab center; 11. Injured soldiers and nurses attending various events; 12. Oslo, people at a harvest festival; 13. France, French prisoners at POW camp are inspected; 14. Paris, people at a market; 15. Engineers building a bridge; 16. N. Africa, Italian and Somalian troops advance through desert; 17. Hiafa, Italian planes bomb British oil tanks; 18. German Stukas take off and dive bomb over England.
    - Reel 530
      1. Rugen, Germany, Ley inspects new construction of seaside resort; 2. Danzig, Dr. Ley inspects housing construction; 3. Hirschau, building of new bridges; 4. Danzig, Goebbels, Gauleiter Foster arriving for first year celebration of Danzig annexation; 5. Danzig, Gauleiter Foster gives new flags to people; 6. Alsace-Lorraine, garrison town for German regiment; 7. Channel Coast, building of airfields; 8. Soldiers bringing bombs to airfield; 9. Bombers and fighters over England; 10. Romania, German planes protect oil fields.
      11. Bucharest, German planes land and crews greet them; 12. Romania, German instruction officers meeting with Romanian officers; 13. Venice, Mussolini reviews troops; 14. Marseille, Hitler, Marshall Pétain meeting together as Hitler tours France; 15. Oct. 23, 1940, Hitler and Franco meet for first time; 16. Hitler and Goering talking on train; 17. Florence, Mussolini, Hitler, Ciano, von Ribbentrop greet at train station then take car to meeting.
    - Reel 531
      1. Germany, women and men harvesting field; 2. Salzburg, laborers in quarry blast materials for autobahn; 3. Germany, party official at opening of glider school; 4. Poland, Victor Lutze on visit to Poland; 5. Posen, Lutze celebrates liberation from Polish government; 6. Warsaw, same liberation celebrations; 7. Warsaw, Himmler, memorial celebration of troops killed in Polish occupation.
    - Reel 532, 1940 November
      1. Belgrade, King Paul and wife Olga, German architecture exhibit; 2. Albania, workers building bridges and streets; 3. Italy, Mussolini inspects 8th Army of Italy; 4. Munich, Rudolf Hess represents Hitler at memorial ceremony for Nazi martyrs killed in 1923; 5. Prague, Axman dedicates new banner to youth; 6. Prague, Goebbels, Baron von Neurath, Burckel in the city to talk about German culture.
      7. Poland, German troops help clear land for farms; 8. Danzig, kindergarten; 9. Engineers build pontoon bridge under fire; 10. Flanders, Italian pilots join Germans on British air raids; 11. Channel Coast, Luftwaffe shoots down Spitfire; 12. German U-Boats leave port; 13. German ships sink British cargo ships.
    - Reel 533, 1940 November
      1. Manchukuo, China, reconstruction of town to modernize it; 2. Indo-China, Japanese troops going through French controlled territory; 3. Amsterdam, Dutch Nazi party parading through the city; 4. Slovakia, glider school for Slovenians; 5. Berlin, sport festival between Germany and Finland; 6. Berlin, Goebbels attends funeral; 7. Berlin, Goebbels, Todt, and Hitler, dinner for war merit medal winners.
      8. Nov. 12, 1940, Molotov, von Ribbentrop, Goering, Hitler, Molotov arrives by train and meets with Hitler; 9. Poland, German troops rebuild streets; 10. Wartegau, workers build new housing; 11. Children and parents on vacation; 12. Berlin, German anti-aircraft in action and downing British ships; 13. Langenmark, von Brauschitz, memorial celebration of dead soldiers from World War I; 14. Oslo, graves of parachute forces; 15. Engineers build bridge; 16. Channel Coast, artillery crews fire at Britain; 17. Luftwaffe attacks British convoy.
    - Reel 534
      Part 1 has no description available.
      1. Gen. Antonescau, von Ribbentrop, Kurusu, Prince Chosa, all signing alliance; 2. Berlin, Slovakian representative meets with Ribbentrop to sign treaty; 3. Vienna, Goering visits exhibit called "Victory in the West"; 4. Westwald, new class of working corps and French war prisoners dismantle Maginot Line; 5. Norway, supplies for German troops unloaded; 6. Channel Coast, Goering awards airmen Iron Crosses; 7. Germany, oil tank cars brought to airfield; 8. Nov. 15, reprisal attack from RAF attack of Munich; 9. North Sea, U-Boat returns from mission.
    - Reel 535
      1. Tokyo, Emperor Hirohito on white horse reviews parade for 2,600th anniversary of Japanese royal family; 2. Italy, Vesuvius erupting; 3. Italy, workers construct power plant; 4. Romania and Austria, German repatriates arrive in Germany; 5. Production of wooden chess figures, among others.
      6. Berlin, Maxi and Ernst Baier, ice skating exhibition for soldiers; 7. Vienna, von Schirach and Todt inspect exhibit of Austrian painters; 8. Lenz, POWs work on autobahn bridge; 9. France, French POWs being sent to Germany for work; 10. French POWs work on bridge; 11. Polish civilians rebuild streets; 12. Bicycle troops; 13. Infantry and tank maneuvers; 14. Airmen load large bombs onto planes bound for London; 15. London, King and Queen, Churchill inspect major damage to London, material from US newsreels.
    - Reel 536
      1. Kunming, China, Japanese planes attack Chinese supply centers; 2. Bucharest, Antonescau, von Schirach lay wreath at grave; 3. Oslo, Goebbels visits graveyards of German war heroes; 4. Poland, laborers work on hydroelectric power plant; 5. German civilians participate in seminar on Africa; 6. Lenz, new housing for factory workers; 7. German teens collect toys for soldiers; 8. Field post office handing out mail to troops; 9. Channel Coast, delivery of mail to happy troops; 10. Trucks leave France for Berlin with food for women and children.
      11. Berlin, Goebbels, concert from German Radio Service for troops; 12. Stienmark, mountain troops in artillery exercise; 13. Bombers loaded with heavy bomb and fire bombs for attack on Birmingham; 14. Kiel, Admiral Raeder inspects Battleship Bismarck and puts it to sea.
    - Reel 537
      Complete reel
      1. Poland, wounded German soldiers at rehab center; 2. Poland, von Brauchitsch reviews troops in east; 3. Bucharest, Antonescau, King Michael review parade of German Wehrmacht troops; 4. Map of Norway compared to Europe and roads needed; 5. German troops transport food; 6. Oslo, new German recruits sworn in; 7. Crew of French RR rebuild road and bridge; 8. Paris, Alfred Rosenberg addresses Chamber of Deputies; 9. Paris, French youth collect clothing; 10. German wounded soldiers make toys for kids; 11. Kids sing to wounded soldiers; 12. Shipyard workers build U-Boats; 13. Hitler, Ley speaks to munition workers at factory.
    - Reel 538
      1. Burma Road, Japanese planes bomb road and factory; 2. Spain, Spanish kids return and are cared for by nurses; 3. Warsaw, retrospect of occupation and new roads, sign on car says "Only for Jews"; 4. Poland, German border guards patrol mountain pass; 5. Norway, German soldiers build new airfields with planes protecting from above; 6. Berlin, Hitler gives reception for industrial, party, and army leaders; 7. Steier, factory workers making rifles.
      Part 2: Christmas Week
      8. Prof. Thorak sets up sculptures; 9. Wartegau, German kids sent on vacation and get gifts; 10. Poland, German troops cut down Christmas tree; 11. Boat leaves Germany with load of presents for troops in Norway; 12. Wounded soldiers and nurses on hospital ship on Christmas Eve; 13. Motorcycle riders transport tree; 14. Soldier dressed as Santa comes out of plane for troops; 15. Soldiers on front receive gifts; 16. NCO gets Ritter Cross; 17. Cavalry troops clean saddle; 18. Captured English submarine; 19. German troops on way to replace troops in Jersey.
    - Reel 539
      Ausland version only.
    - Reel 540
      1. Tacoma, Washington, professor from University of Washington inspects bridge oscillating in high winds, taken from US newsreel; 2. Paris, Legionnaires carry casket of French pilot shot down by RAF; 3. Adm. Darlan awards medals; 4. Vienna and Paris, Adm. Darlan receives body of son of Napoleon and places body in tomb; 5. Poland, traveling exhibition; 6. Wartegau, German youth training; 7. Berlin, Goebbels, Hitler, Victor Lutze, 50th birthday celebration; 8. Norway, German troops buy deer meat; 9. Crews of mine sweeping flotilla; 10. Recon plane sees enemy ships and signals back; 11. France, infantry and artillery maneuvers.
    - Reel 541
      1. Tokyo, Emperor Hirohito, memorial and parade for fallen heroes; 2. Yangzi, Japanese planes bomb mountain areas; 3. Mexico City, Gen. Avilla Camacho, folk dances by youth; 4. Geneva, civilian workers at Red Cross center, records of war prisoners; 5. Jan. 12, Goering's 48th birthday; 6. France, workers being trained on German equipment; 7. Warsaw, laborers build canals and bridges; 8. Krakow, entertainment for soldiers; 9. Norway, occupying troops build new roads and barracks; 10. N. France, war reporters collect money for "mother and child" fund; 11. War booty collected; 12. Flight training school; 13. Crew of heavy cruiser puts to sea and sinks British freighter.
    - Reel 542
      1. Tokyo, Hirohito and German delegation celebrate 2,600 years of Emperor's family; 2. Moscow, Molotov, Count von Schulenburg, signing of 4 new treaties; 3. Civilians in heavy snow throughout Europe; 4. Norway, flotilla of Norwegian fishing boats; 5. Denmark, German sailors sightsee at castle; 6. Holland, parade for 9 years of Dutch Nazis; 7. Hirchau, Poland, Foster, building bridge for Autobahn; 8. Posen, reconstruction of theater of Posen; 9. Berlin, art exhibit; 10. Berlin, continuation of Goering's birthday celebration; 11. Production of large aerial search lights; 12. S. France, motorcycle shock troops training; 13. Lt. Col. Gallant attacks RAF planes.
    - Reel 543
      Complete reel; names of 9 cameramen